<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>k3s on Terence Lau</title>
    <link>https://blog.cklau.cc/tags/k3s/</link>
    <description>Recent content in k3s on Terence Lau</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2005–2022, Terence Junjie LIU; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2022 10:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.cklau.cc/tags/k3s/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>K3s/Kubernetes - Set up a K3s Cluster with your VPS (Extra Story 1)</title>
      <link>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k3s-setup-extra-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2022 10:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k3s-setup-extra-1/</guid>
      <description>As I have mentioned in K3s Setup 2, usually, it is not easy for the China&amp;rsquo;s user to access https://gcr.io, https://k8s.gcr.io or https://ghcr.io. Thus, under this circumstance, we may set up a server as the registry proxy endpoint.
Some options DockerHub provide a &amp;ldquo;offical&amp;rdquo; package called Docker Registry where it is a stateless, hightly scalable server side application that stores and lets users distribute Docker images.
Nexus Repository OSS, provided by Sonatype, is an open source repository that supports many artifact formats, including Docker, Java™, and npm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>K3s/Kubernetes - Set up a K3s Cluster with your VPS (2)</title>
      <link>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k3s-setup-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:11:21 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k3s-setup-2/</guid>
      <description>Generating a basic K3s cluster is quite easy by following the K3s&amp;rsquo;s Doc. let try to modify it into High Availability Cluster. Single server cluster can meet a variety of use cases, but for environments where uptime of the Kubenetes control plane is critical, where we need the High Availability configuration. There are two ways for High Availability:
 High Availability with an External DB (for example, PostgreSQL, MySQL, MariaDB) High Availability with Embedded DB (etcd)  I chose the second one - with Embedded DB.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>K3s/Kubernetes - From K3s to Kubernetes: Set up a Kubernetes in a nutshell (1)</title>
      <link>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k8s-setup-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:11:21 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k8s-setup-1/</guid>
      <description>Before What is Kuberntes Kubernetes, is an open-source system for automating deployment, scaling, and management of containerized applications. Usually, we call it K8s as there are 8 characters between K and s :).
Basically, all the application are containerized, and we can easily the reason why we use K8s is that the use of microservices increasing, away from traditional monolithic-type applications. As a result, containers provide the perfeet host form these individual microservices as containers manage dependencies, are indipendent, OS-agnostic and ephemaral, amongst other benefits, which is very powerful and suitable for users as we want users to run their application isolated and donot be influenced by others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>K3s/Kubernetes - Set up a K3s Cluster with your VPS (1)</title>
      <link>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k3s-setup-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:11:21 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.cklau.cc/post/k3s-setup-1/</guid>
      <description>Before K3s is a lightweight Kubernetes which is more suitable for the Edge/IoT/CI/ARM scenario/devices. Usually, for person, we do not have multiple high-performance device like 24c server or even higher. Hence, K3s is a way we can learn how to set up a kubernetes cluster.
For me, I am a bare metal fanatic many year ago, but I changed into a Docker user after I know more about virtualization and containers.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
